Guide to the Pennsylvania Speech Association Records, 1939-1969 AIS.1967.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Speech Association Records
1939-1969
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Speech Association
AIS.1967.03
2.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The Pennsylvania Speech Association records document the internal and external communications and workings of this professional association. The materials reflect the evolution in speech education in Pennsylvania between 1939 and 1969.
History
The Pennsylvania Speech Association was created in 1939 with the mission to improve the instruction of speech and speech programs, remove speech defects, assess the nature and extent of speech problems in Pennsylvania, and put into effect possible solutions to these problems. The association attempted to achieve these goals through the publishing a newsletter for its members and The Pennsylvania Speech Annual, a professional journal. The organization was primarily composed of professionals in the field of speech and related professionals interested in the subject.
The Pennsylvania Speech Association changed its name to the Speech Communication Association of Pennsylvania in 1972. A third change in the organizations name occurred in 2003 when it became the Pennsylvania Communications Association in 2003. The modern organization aims to promote teaching, research, service, and development in all areas of human communication. Throughout its lifetime the organization has consistently published the Annual, a statewide journal, and it has awarded members of the public for their contribution to the field of speech.
Significant individuals associated with this organization include William Tacey and John Henry Frizzell. William Tacey was born in New York in 1904. After graduating from Geneva College with bachelor's degree he began teaching at McKeesport High School where he became the debate coach in 1938. He remained in McKeesport until 1946 when he was invited to teach at Pennsylvania State University. Due to a housing shortage he soon returned to the Pittsburgh area where he began teaching at the University of Pittsburgh in 1947. His teaching career encompassed all levels of education as well as the private sector, having worked for U.S. Steel, Duquesne Light, and Westinghouse Electric among others. Tacey was involved in a variety of speech organizations where he held a multitude of positions, including chairman of the Speech Education Committee of the Pennsylvania Speech Association. He also held the positions of president, vice-president, and secretary for the American Association of University Professors and it is through this contribution that he is best remembered by an award which bears his name. John Henry Frizzell was a chaplain and a professor, serving as a faculty member at Pennsylvania State College where he taught public speaking. He eventually became the head of the speech department at the college and served as the first president of the Pennsylvania Speech Association.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The Pennsylvaia Speech Association records are arranged in twelve series:
Series I. Awards
Series II. Committees
Series III. Conferences/Conventions
Series IV. Constitutions
Series V. Correspondence
Series VI. Meeting Minutes
Series VII. Member Directories
Series VIII. Newsletters
Series IX. Pennsylvania High School Speech League
Series X. Pennsylvania State University
Series XI. Publications
Series XII. Topical Folders
Scope and Content Notes
Records include a variety of administrative materials including: bylaws, constitutions, minutes, correspondence, planning materials for annual conference/convention, and committee records. Also included are various communication tools such as membership directories, newsletters, and other publications.
Previous Citation
Pennsylvania Speech Association Records, 1939-1969, AIS.1967.03, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Custodial History
This collection was originally placed in the care of the Special Collections Department of the University Library System in 1967. It was transferred to the Archives Service Center in September of 2012.
Related Material
Individual issues of The Pennsylvania Speech Annual are located at the University of Pittsburgh at both Hillman Library and the ULS Storage facility.
William Tacey Papers, 1924-1983, UA.90.F9, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Education; Associations; Speech -- Study and teaching -- Pennsylvania; Speech therapy -- Pennsylvania; Harrisburg (Pa.); Altoona (Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Bethlehem (Pa.); Constitutions; Proceedings (Reports); Newsletters; Correspondence; Tacey, William Sanford; Fairless, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin); Pennsylvania High School Speech League; University of Pittsburgh; Pennsylvania State University; Pennsylvania Speech Association; Frizzell, John Henry
- Awards, 1953-1965; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The awards series contains eight folders, each of which is assigned a year between 1953 and 1965. Each year corresponds to one or two individuals who were presented with the 'Award for Distinction in the Art of Speech Used in the Service of Mankind' from the Pennsylvania Speech Association. These individuals range from teachers to business professionals and include both men and women.
  - Benjamin Fairless, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daniel A. Poling, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James Stewart, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Everett Hunt, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Janet Blair and Jennie Blatchford, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Charles Nutting, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cloyd Harkins, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Beryl McLean and Emma Miller, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committees, 1949-1959; II.
  The committee series contains seven folders, each corresponding to a specific group within the Pennsylvania Speech Association. Each folder contains either bylaws or other material for that specific committee.
  - Committee Bylaws for the Clinical Speech and Hearing Division (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee Bylaws for the General Speech Division (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee Bylaws for the Speech Arts Division (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Oral Interpretation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Public Relations, 1949-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Committee on Speech Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Conferences/Conventions, 1940-1961; III.
  The conferences/conventions series contains 21 folders, each corresponding to one or multiple statewide meetings that the Pennsylvania Speech Association held annually. The folders predominately contain association registration forms, convention calls, and convention agendas.
  - Second Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Third Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fourth Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fifth Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sixth Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Seventh Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fifth Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sixth Annual Conference at Harrisburg, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Seventh Annual Conference at Harrisburg, Conference Material, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Seventh Annual Conference at Harrisburg, Registration Forms, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Eighth Annual Conference at Altoona, Conference Material, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Eighth Annual Conference at Altoona, Registration Forms A-C, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Eighth Annual Conference at Altoona, Registration Forms D-J, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Eighth Annual Conference at Altoona, Registration Forms K-N, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Eighth Annual Conference at Altoona, Registration Forms O-Z, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Ninth Annual Conference at Altoona, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Annual Conference at Pittsburgh, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Annual Conference, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Folder thirty-three contains material for the annual conferences of 1955, which took place in Philadelphia, and of 1956, which took place in Bethlehem.
  - Annual Conference, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Folder thirty-four contains material for the annual conferences of 1957, which took place in Altoona, of 1958, which took place in Greensburg, of 1959, which took place in Philadelphia, of 1964, which took place in Philadelphia, of 1965, which took place in Pittsburgh, of 1968, and of an undated annual conference.
  - Annual Conference Registration Forms, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Convention Districts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Constitutions, 1948-1964; IV.
  The constitution series contains four folders. The constitutions range 16 years and show how the Pennsylvania Speech Association evolved by changing and updated its goals and the stipulations for membership.
  - 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Proposed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Correspondence, 1939-1969; V.
  The correspondence series contains 74 folders, each of which corresponds to a specific year or genre of discourse. The majority of the series consists of correspondents between individuals, of which at least one of the two members is part of the association or its administration. There are two folders that do not follow this particular style and they are the general correspondence to all members, which consists of items sent from the association to multiple individuals, and internal correspondence, which is predominately letters sent from either the executive secretary or the president to other member of the administration.
  - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 1942 (Box 1, Folder 44-47)
  - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
  - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 53-60)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 61-67)
  - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 68-73)
  - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 74-76)
  - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 77-81)
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 83-86)
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 87-94)
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 95-100)
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 101-104)
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 105-108)
  - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - General Correspondence to all Members, 1939-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Internal Correspondence, 1939-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Meeting Minutes, 1939-1966; VI.
  The meeting minutes series contains three folders, each of which corresponds to multiple years of materials. Items in this series are records of either the executive committee or various association committees. These records are both hand-written and typed and cover a variety of topics such as convention planning and journal submissions.
  - 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1942-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Member Directories, 1945-1966; VII.
  The member directories series contains 12 folders, each of which corresponds to either a specific type of directories or multiple years of general member directories. The general member directories include personal information about members such as their name, address, and occasionally their profession or field of study within the topic of speech.
  - 1945/1946-1947/1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1948/1949-1950/1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1951/1952-1954/1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1955/1956-1957/1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1958/1959-1959/1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1961/1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Directory of Administrators, 1952-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Directory of Non-Members (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Directory of Speech and Hearing Personnel, 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Directory of Volunteer Speech Consultants, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Directory Supplements, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - First Meeting Attendance List, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Newsletters, 1939-1965; VIII.
  The newsletters series contains 12 folders, each of which corresponds to one or multiple years of the newsletter produced by the association. The newsletter contains information such as the date and location of the conferences, meeting minutes, financial reports, list of officers, list of members, committee material, and other news.
  - 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1962; 1965 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Pennsylvania High School Speech League, 1961-1965; IX.
  The Pennsylvania High School Speech League series contains ten folders consisting of the speech league material, newsletters in particular, ranging from 1961-1965. This material shows how the Pennsylvania Speech Association influenced the education of speech in universities and colleges. Robert Dunham is listed as the director of the speech league on all of the newsletters. While acting as director he was a professor at Pennsylvania State University beginning in 1959 and the executive secretary for the Pennsylvania Speech Association beginning in 1964.
  - Constitution Drafts and Final Copy (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Newsletter, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Newsletter, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Newsletter, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - Newsletter, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Pamphlets, Event Calendar, and Letter from the Department Head (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Tournament Material (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Pennsylvania State University, 1950-1969; X.
  The Pennsylvania State University series contains seven folders relating to the university's speech department and those affiliated with it, such as Dr. Oliver and the Speech Department students. Dr. Oliver was president of the Pennsylvania Speech Association in 1954, and president of the Speech Association of American in 1964. Due to his contributions, both on and off campus, Pennsylvania State University has a lifetime award for Speech Education that bears his name.
  - Dr. Oliver's Student Reviews (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Executive Workshop Agenda (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - List of Students Associated with the Speech Department (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Speech 0200 Lecture, Post-1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Speech 0502 Syllabus, Post-1963 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Speech Department Newsletter, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Test, Test Key, and Scantrons (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Publications (Various), 1940-1968; XI.
  The publications series consists of two folders that contain various printed speeches, articles, reports and other leaflets. This includes reports on early educational television.
  - 1940-1952 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 1953-1968 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Topical Folders, XII.
  The topical folders contain material relating to the running of the organization, such as administrative papers, election information, and speeches.
  - Agendas (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Auditorium Activities Roundtable (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Certification for Secondary School Teachers (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Code of Ethics (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Election Material (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Financial Reports (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Guidelines for Contributors to he Pennsylvania Speech Annual Journal (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Officer Duties (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Presidential Messages and Memorandums (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Reports, 1940-1954 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Reports, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Resolutions (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Speech Association of the Eastern States (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Speeches and Speech Excerpt (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Surveys (Box 2, Folder 64)